Guide to the Carlos Salzedo papers MS 679
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Carlos Salzedo Papers
1930-2002
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Salzedo, Carlos (Carlos Léon Salzedo)
MS 679
3.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection includes autograph music manuscripts, annotated and signed published scores, articles, photos, and notebooks of harpist, composer, and teacher Carlos Salzedo. There are also materials about Alice Chalifoux, Salzedo's student and an influential harpist and teacher in her own right.
Biographical / Historical
Carlos Salzedo (1885-1961) was a French harpist, pianist, composer and conductor. He began playing piano by the age of three, and wrote and published his first composition, a polka called Moustique (Mosquito), when he was five years old. At twelve years old he began studying the harp, and within a year was accepted as a harp student in the Paris Conservatoire. In 1909, Arturo Toscanini invited Salzedo to play in the orchestra of the Metropolitan Opera, and Salzedo moved to New York. From the 1920s onward, Salzedo appeared regularly as a soloist with orchestras such as the Philadelphia Orchestra, and on tour as a recitalist, harp ensemble leader and flute-harp-cello trio member. Salzedo is regarded by many as one of history's greatest harpists, and he was a highly regarded pianist, conductor, and teacher as well. His transcriptions and compositions were original and well abreast of the latest musical developments. He was a progressive spirit, seeking new tonal resources in the improved harp of his day manufactured by Lyon & Healy. Salzedo taught hundreds of students during his career, and inspired other composers with his unique works and style of playing.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes autograph music manuscripts, annotated and signed published scores, articles, photos, and notebooks of harpist, composer, and teacher Carlos Salzedo. There are also materials about Alice Chalifoux, Salzedo's student and an influential harpist and teacher in her own right.
Access Restrictions
These materials are available for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were donated by Rice University Shepherd School of Music Harp professor Paula Page in 2017 and 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Composition (Music); Harpists; Harp; Composers; Music
Subjects (Persons)
Chalifoux, Alice
- Series I: Autograph Music Manuscripts
  - Short Stories in Music for Young Harpists, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 15 Preludes for Beginners (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cadenza for Capriccio Espagnol (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sonata in one movement for Harp and Piano, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Idée Fixe (signed copy of autograph music manuscript), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Copies of autograph music manuscripts, unsigned (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Printed Musical Scores
  - Scores transcribed for harp, annotated and signed by Salzedo (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scores transcribed for harp, signed by Salzedo (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Debussy's Childrens's Corner, copies of transcriptions for harp, flute, and cello by Salzedo (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Harp Concerto in B flat, Handel, score and parts annotated by Salzedo (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Conte Fantastique, André Caplet, parts annotated by Salzedo, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Four notebooks on Timing of Compositions (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Photographs of Salzedo, 1931-1950's (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Articles
  - Magazine articles about Salzedo, 1946-1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Articles on harp by Salzedo, 1930-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Journal articles about Salzedo, 1939-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Series V: Documents
  - Correspondence, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Alice Chalifoux
  - Salzedo Ensemble programs (Jeanne Chalifoux), 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Salzedo Ensemble itineraries, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Summer Harp Colony of America (The Salzedo School), 1961-2001 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Class photos of The Salzedo School, 1970-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Articles, newsclippings on Alice Chalifoux, 1930-2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Articles on harp performance, 1984-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Oversized Materials
  - Posters, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Slate with 12 tone scale (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings, 1936-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Drawing of Salzedo Harp Trunk (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Harp Concerto, manuscript copy, Alberto Ginastera, ca. 1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Series VIII: Music manuscripts and scores
  - Conditioning Exercises (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Prélude, Ravel, transcribed for harp by Salzedo, autograph music manuscript, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chanson dans la Nuit, second harp, autograph music manuscript, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Diptych Reflets Interference, signed copy of autograph music manuscript, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Siete Canciones Populares Españolas, Mañuel de Falla, transcribed for two harps, Salzedo, signed copies of autograph music manuscripts, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 5)